

Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com www.LondonResearchInternational.com

Ms. Read

NATIONALITY: British/ South African

SUMMARY

Ms.Read is a highly experienced Environmental Consultant, who also runs her own consulting firm in Cape Town, South Africa. She also has experiences working with the United Nations Development Program: Africa Adaptation Programme (AAP) from April 2010 to January 2012. Being fluent in English, she has worked in London, United Kingdom as well, as an environmental consultant. Her experienced countries are as followed: South Africa, Rwanda, Ethiopia, Tanzania, Senegal, Kenya, Namibia and Lesotho.

She has also achieved various voluntary work in Cape Town, for example, she was a volunteer consultant in Tearfund Christian Relief and Development Agency from 2008 to 2009, assisting the environmental assessment team in the creation of an environmental assessment guideline tool to be utilized in developing countries with little existing environmental legislation.

EDUCATION

- University o Cape Town, South Africa, 2002-2004
 BSs, Environmental and Geographical Science and Social Anthropology
- Rustenburg high School for Girls, South Africa, 1997-2001
 Matriculation Exemption

EMPLOYMENT RECORD/PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

- Victoria Read Environmental Consulting, June 2013-current, South Africa Principle Consultant/ Owner
 - > Specialised in the implementation of environmental legislation and ensuring client compliance with the relevant regulations;
 - Offer the following services to clients: Full Scoping and EIA Processes, Basic Assessment Processes, 24G Rectification Processes, Public Participation, Peer Review of Environmental Documentation, Ad hoc report writing for larger consultancies, Environmental Management Programmes etc.;



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com www.LondonResearchInternational.com

Focussed particularly on the agricultural and rural development sector.

Chand Environmental Consultants, March 2012- Current, South Africa Senior Environmental Consultants

Responsible for the management and coordination of all South African National Environmental Management Act related projects namely; Basic Assessment processes, Scoping and Environmental Impact Assessments; Environmental

Management Programmes and 24G Rectification processes;

- > Specialised in the implementation of environmental law, guidelines and policies in order to advise clients and other relevant stakeholders;
- Management of junior staff and review of all documentation produced;
- Management and liaison with all relevant specialists required for input into environmental impact assessments;
- Involved in creative problem solving as well as conflict management when dealing with complex public participation processes;
- ➤ Campaigner for environmental rights through the implementation and correct interpretation of the environmental legislation and relevant regulations.

United Nations Development Program: Africa Adaptation Program (APP), April 2010- Jan 2012

Climate Change and Capacity Development Advisor

- Implementation Specialist In-Country (Ethiopia): April 2010 January 2011
 - Provided in-country assistance to the United Nations Development Programme, Ethiopian Country Office as well as the Ethiopian Environmental Protection Authority (EPA) for the implementation of the Africa Adaptation Programme (AAP);
 - Responsible for initiating projects which would support long term, climate resilient development in Ethiopia and the overall objectives of the AAP;
 - Advised the government (EPA) on methods for mainstreaming climate resilient policies and measures into priority sectors;
 - o Developed and implemented the monthly and annual workplans in



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com www.LondonResearchInternational.com

conjunction with local project staff and other partner organisations namely: the World Food Programme and the United Nations Children's Fund;

- Supervised and provided technical support for a team of 10-15 local project staff and research assistants;
- Budgeting and financial backstopping support for the \$1.3 million project;
- Produced presentation material on the AAP and provided climate change awareness training to stakeholders e.g. the Ethiopian media, Parliamentarians, NGO's and civil society;
- Assisted in forging key partnerships between the AAP and NASA, World Resources Institute and DFID (UK Aid);
- Provided feedback and monthly activity reports to the Inter-regional Technical Support Component of the AAP project based in Senegal;
- Produced news articles and journal pieces to document progress on the project for internal UN communications as well as external media.
- Regional Advisor for the Professional Development Program (PDP): January 2011- January 2012
 - Project managed the AAP's Professional Development Programme which assisted national AAP project managers, governments and UN agencies develop the knowledge and skills to strengthen their capacity to implement the national

AAP projects and other climate change related projects effectively;

Responsible for the execution of the PDP workshops in Tanzania,
 Kenya and Morocco which aimed at optimising the effectiveness of project implementation in countries, training the leaders on climate change, developing technical

knowledge and skills of those in the climate change field and positively direct their personal growth:

- Provided in-country ongoing support post workshops in the following countries; Rwanda, Ethiopia, Tanzania, Senegal, Kenya, Namibia, Lesotho, and Mauritius and provided an advisory role to the remaining 12 AAP African countries;
- o Planned and produced all learning materials, and implemented many



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com www.LondonResearchInternational.com

practical educational activities during the workshops and all reporting post workshops;

- Managed the admin team of 5 local staff members in the Senegal UNOPS support office in order to execute the workshops, each hosting over 80 African delegates.
- Department of Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA), Oct 2008-Jan 2010, London, United Kingdom
 Higher Executive Officer
- Environ, Apr 2008-Oct 2008, London, United Kingdom Environmental Consultant
- Ninham Shand Consulting Services, Feb 2007-Mar 2008, South Africa Environmental Practitioner

There are other experiences in the area of environmental affairs and development consulting since 2005, mainly in Cape Town (South Africa)

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

n/a

PUBLICATIONS

- Boabab Coalition Journal 2011: Contribution to the article 'Professional Development for development professionals'.
- World Resources Report 2010-2011: Acknowledged as an external reviewer for the 2010-2011 World Resources Report which provides policy analysis for critical issues arising from human dependence and impacts on the environment.
- Tearfund Environmental Assessment Tool 2009: Acknowledged for contributions to the guideline document on the implementation of environmental assessments for medium-impact projects written for developing countries.



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com
www.LondonResearchInternational.com

A 8	٧G	 A 4		$\boldsymbol{\Gamma}$
 1 2 I	u	 ΔІ	-	

English